Finding Aid for M. R. DeHaan publications, undated and 1934-1940s
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
M. R. DeHaan publications undated and 1934-1940s
DeHaan, M.R. (Martin Ralph), 1891-1965.
1 box
[739] DA 2; D322; S486
Evangelical minister based in Grand Rapids, Michigan whose Radio Bible Class was broadcast on the Mutual Radio network.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from several sources.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Martin Ralph DeHaan (commonly know as M. R. DeHaan) was born in Zeeland, Michigan in 1891. He was raised in the Reformed Church of America and attended Hope College for a year before transferring to the University of Illinois, Chicago to study medicine. He eventually set up a family practice in western Michigan. A personal medical emergency in 1921 led to a conversion experience that led DeHaan to sell his practice and enroll at Western Theological Seminary. There he became a convert to dispensational premillenialism and an opponent of infant baptism.
DeHaan lead a parish in Grand Rapids for nine years. His often contentious tenure ended when he resigned after suffering a heart attack in 1938. He then taught evening bible classes, and at the urging of his mentor William McCarrell, began broadcasting his classes on a small Detroit radio station. In 1941 the Mutual Network began carrying his radio Bible Class. After DeHaan suffered a second heart attack while on the air in 1946, and his son Richard assumed more and more responsibility for the broadcast and management of DeHaan's organization.
DeHaan authored twenty-five books and his organization, Radio Bible Class, of Grand Rapids continued to publish a daily devotional booklet Our Daily Bread.
DeHaan died in 1965.
Sources: Encyclopedia of Evangelicalism.
The M. R. DeHaan collection consist of printed copies of sermons delivered by DeHaan.
Subjects:
DeHaan, M. R. (Martin Ralph), 1891-1965.; Sermons--AmMerican.
- Sermons
  - Antichrist (Box 1)
  - Backside of the desert
  - Baptized in the spirit
  - Broken things and new things. 1939
  - Burning bush
  - Chemistry of tears
  - Christian education. March, 1941
  - Coming of the King. November, 1940
  - Divine healing
  - End of the world
  - Faith and works
  - Forgotten man of Christmas
  - Fractional Christians
  - Grace of giving. January 14, 1934
  - He is coming again. January, 1941
  - Hell and Hades
  - His Majesty - the Devil
  - Image of God
  - Jonah and the whale. Reprint, October 27, 1937
  - Judgment seat of Christ
  - Kingdom of Heaven
  - Law and grace
  - Lie detector in the light of scripture
  - Lost axe head
  - Many infallible proofs
  - Marriage, divorce and re-marriage
  - Methuselah
  - New creation January, 1941
  - Peace in a world of war. May, 1941
  - Place called Calvary
  - Prince of Peace
  - Rapture of the Church
  - Resurrection. April, 1941
  - Rods of God. May 10, 1936
  - Royal honeymoon
  - Sabbath or the Lord's day
  - Science of redemption
  - Seed of Abraham
  - Seven laws of separation. 1934
  - Sin unto death. 1934
  - Social justice
  - That blessed hope
  - Third hour. 1934
  - V is for victory
  - Virgin birth
  - We would see Jesus